A Guide to the Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Escheated Estates records, 1779-1874
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts - Escheated Estates records, 1779-1874
The Library of Virginia
APA 658
1.05 cu. ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia Auditor of Public Accounts (1776-1928)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Auditor of Public Accounts in 1913.
Biographical Information
During its session begun in May 1779 the General Assembly passed an act forbidding British subjects to hold real or personal property; any such property would be forfeited, or escheat, to the states. The escheated estates were sold and the proceeds were kept in the state treasury. A one-month period was set aside during which an individual might come forward and establish a claim to the proceeds from the sale of property but not title to the property. Commissioners of the sale for escheated estates certified to whom and for how much the sale was made and informed the auditor of public accounts.
In 1785 the General Assembly passed an act authorizing the appointment of an escheator by the governor for each locality. An act was passed in December 1797 to permit escheators to sell land on credit if they thought it would enhance the price. The purchaser signed a deed of trust and a bond, copies of which were sent to the auditor.
Scope and Content
Escheated Estates Records, 1779-1874, containing accounts, bonds, deeds of trust, proceedings, and resolutions. The bulk of the collection are the accounts with escheators, arranged alphabetically by city or county name. The accounts show the sale of confiscated land, personal property, crops [timber, tobacco], and slaves. The accounts list the owner of the escheated estates and often include the name of the new owners. The accounts also payed out fees to the court, salaries to escheators, summoning a jury, sheriff fees, and advertising fees. The largest number of estates were in Norfolk County.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by folder title. Oversize materials were separated and placed in an oversize box though everything is listed in alphabetical order in the finding aid. Researchers should pay special attention to note the box numbers.
Contents List
- Accounts - Amelia County, 1816-1823 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  British subject(s): Alexander Willson, dec.
- Accounts - Bedford County, 1814-1817 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  British subject(s): James Ewing, Jacob Robinson
- Accounts - Botetourt County, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  British subject(s): John Green
- Accounts - Buckingham County, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  British subject(s): Walther King
- Accounts - Cabell County, 1824-1829 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  British subject(s): John Irwin, dec.; Matthew Jones.
- Accounts - Cabell County [Oversize], 1820-1822 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  British subject(s): James [Ceven?]; John Cholston; William Cofland; Joseph Gatewood; Philip Gatewood; William Hogan; Edward Goodwin; [Mike?] Johnson; Mathew Jones; Richard Morris; Richard Smith; Daniel Staples; Edmund Waggoner; John Wilson
- Accounts - Caroline County, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  British subject(s): O. Dich
- Accounts - Charles City County, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  British subject(s): Amos Ladd, dec.; Elizabeth Minge, dec.; Robert Phillips, dec.
- Accounts - Charlotte County, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Accounts - Chesterfield County, 1782-1840 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  British subject(s): Henry Anderson; Francis Bevill; Edmund Booker; Thomas Broom; Richard Burks; Benjamin Burton; William Burton; Joseph Calvert; Augustine Claiborne; Thomas Coles; James Deans; Edward Driver: Thomas Dudley; John Dunsmore, dec.; Peter Fitzpatrick; John Fleming; John Hambleton; John McLoud [McCleod]; Alexander Mackie; Alexander Marshall; William Marshall; Isaac Michaels, dec.; Robert Pleasants, Jr.; Richard Royall; Walker and Newsum; Nathaniel Young
- Accounts - Chesterfield County [Oversize], 1840 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  British subject(s): Henry Anderson; William Burton; Edmund Booker; Thomas Broom; Francis Bevill; Augustine Claiborne; John Flemming; John Hambleton; Benjmamin Burton; Richard Burks; Thomas Coles; Joseph Calvert; James Deans; Thomas Dudley; Peter Fitzpatrick; Alexander Marshall, William Marshall; Alexander Mackie; Robert Pleasants, Jr.; Richard Royall; Walker & Newsum
- Accounts - Culpeper County, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  British subject(s): Samuel Abbot; Edmund Hasell, dec.
- Accounts - Essex County, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  British subject(s): Lawrence W. Duff; Robert Ferguson; John Ramsay; James Ritchie & Co.; James Wignell
- Accounts - Fairfax County, 1796-1823 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Accounts - Fauquier County, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Accounts - Frederick County, 1798-1799 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Accounts - Hampshire County, 1782-1784 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  British subject(s): Captain Phillip Martin's Patterson Creek Manor; Reverend Jacob Townsand.
- Accounts - Hanover County [Oversize], 1780 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  British subject(s): George Brackenridge; James Esten; Archibald Govern; John Johnson; Alexander McAuly; Donald Scott & Co.; John Smith; John Stewart; George Thomas
- Accounts - Henrico County, 1779-1783 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  British subject(s): Robert Baine
- Accounts - Henrico County, 1795-1797 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  British subject(s): Thomas Calder [Elder], dec.; Overton L. Harvie
- Accounts - Henry County, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  British subject(s): James & Archibald Smith
- Accounts - Isle of Wight County, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  British subject(s): John Goodrich; Hunter & Blair; John Hundman; Oswald & Co.; John Syme; Syme & Co.; John Williams
- Accounts - Isle of Wight County [Oversize], 1779 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  British subject(s): Mr. Hunter & Blair; John Goodrich; John Hyndman; John Lynn; Andrew Lyon & Co.; Oswald & Co.; John Williams
- Accounts - King George County, 1782-1805 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  British subject(s): Orr & Greenlesse
- Accounts - King William County, 1782-1814 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  British subject(s): Archibald Govan; Samuel Walden, dec.
- Accounts - Lunenburg County, 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  British subject(s): William Cunningham & Co.; John Graham; Andrew Johnston; John Paterson [Patterson]
- Accounts - Mecklenburg County, 1780-1790 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  British subject(s): Andrew Cockram, William Cunningham & Co.; Dinwiddie & Co.; Dinwiddie Crawford & Co.; Andrew Johnston, Jr.; Alexander Spur's & Co.
- Accounts - Middlexsex County, 1782, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  British subject(s): Mary Drayton, dec.
- Accounts - Montgomery and Washington Counties, 1781-1782 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Accounts - Nansemond Counties, 1787 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Accounts - Norfolk County, 1780-1805 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  British subject(s): John Agnew; Thomas Applewhaite; John Bellintine; Benjamin Bennerman; George & John Bowness; John Brown; Jamieson Cambell Calvert & Co.; James Campbell & Co.; William Chisholm; John Crammond; Josiah Curling; James Dawson; John Duncan; James Dunn; Jonathan Eilbeck; John Ewing; Thomas Farrar; William Farrar; Robert Gilmour; John Goodrich, Jr.; John Goodrich, Sr.; John Greenwood; John Hardy; John Markham Herbert; Josiah Hodges; William Hodges; Neil Jamieson; Walter King; Benjamin Knight; Thomas McKnight; James Miller; Alexander Montgomry; Willoughby Morgan; William Orange; Daniel Phillips; William Ranking; William Johnson Rysam; Robert Shedden; James Sikes; Joshua Smith; Andrew Sprowle; Andrew Stevenson; Roger Stewart; Thomas Stewart; Talbot Thompson; Collin Wray
- Accounts - Norfolk County [Oversize], 1780-1784 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  British subject(s): George & John Bowness; Jamieson Cambell Calvert & Co.; James Campbell & Co.; John Crammond; Josiah Curling; John Duncan; Robert Gilmour; John Goodrich, Sr.; John Greenwood; John Hardy; John Markam Herbert; William Hodges; Neil Jamieson; Benjamin Knight; Willoughby Morgan; Daniel Phillips; William Johnson Rysam; James Sikes, Jr.; Joshua Smith; Andrew Stevenson; Talbot Thompson; Collin Wray
- Accounts - Northumberland Counties, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  British subject(s): William Campbell
- Accounts - Pendleton County, 1833 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  British subject(s): Adam Bowyer, dec.
- Accounts - Petersburg, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  British subject(s): Charles O'Hara, dec.
- Accounts - Pittsylvania County, 1780-1815 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  British subject(s): John Smith Murdock & Co.
- Accounts - Prince Edward County, 1813-1817 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  British subject(s): John Fisher; John McMurry, dec.
- Accounts - Prince George County, 1782-1783 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  British subject(s): Buchanan Hartie & Co.; Copeland estate; Jane Jamison; John McNabb
- Accounts - Prince William County, 1779-1808 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  British subject(s): Thomas Aitkin; John Goodman
- Accounts - Prince William County [Oversize], 1780 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  British subject(s): Collin Dunlop; John Riddell; James Ritchie
- Accounts - City of Richmond, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  British subject(s): George Johnson, dec.
- Accounts - Rockingham County, 1801-1812 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  British subject(s): Rev. Thomas Jackson, dec.; Henry Stoutsnocker [Stoutsnocher]
- Accounts - Shenandoah County, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Accounts - Southampton County, 1814-1816 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  British subject(s): Alexander McNeal [McNiel], dec.
- Accounts - Stafford County, 1798-1805 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  British subject(s): Richard Gill; John Johnson
- Accounts - Suffolk, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  British subject(s): Estate of Gibson Donoldson & Co.
- Accounts - Sussex County, 1803 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Accounts - Westmoreland County, 1798 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Accounts - Wood County, 1829-1830 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  British subject(s): Rudolph Wildrick [Wildrix], dec.
- Accounts - Unidentified, 1786-1804 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  British subject(s): Robert Irvin, dec.
- Deeds of Trust, 1818-1828 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  George Bell (Prince Edward County); John Connell (Brooke County); James Crockett (Wythe County); William Fenwick (Henrico County); Berryman Green, Sr. (Halifax County); William Holland (Prince Edward County); John Ledwidge and George James (Spotsylvania County); Richard and Ann Ligon (Amelia County); John Morris (Prince Edward County); William Patton (Brooke County); Jacob Price (Prince Edward County); Matthew H. and Catharine Rice (City of Richmond); Benjamin Thackston (Prince Edward County); Charles Woodson, Robert Kelso, Nathaniel Price, James D. Wood, and Samuel C. Anderson (Prince Edward County)
- Deeds of Trust [Oversize], 1818-1822 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  John Elson (City of Richmond); Obadiah Gathright and Adolph Dill (City of Richmond); Philip Haxall (City of Richmond); William Hewett (Stafford County); Joseph and Margaret Jones (Stafford County); Edward C. Mayo (City of Richmond); James and Mary Robertson (Stafford County); John Stannard Marshall (Stafford County); Claiborn and Lavinia Wigglesworth (Stafford County)
- Proceedings and Resolutions, 1779-1804 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  British subject(s): John Crammond; John Goodrich & Co.
- Proceedings [Oversize], 1798-1799 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  A list of lands returned by the Commissioners of the Revenue as the property of the Commonwealth (Counties A-W)